Inventory of the Milovan Djilas papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Milovan Djilas papers
1931-1989
80128
Hoover Institution Archives
43 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box, 378 digital image files (.007 GB) (18.3 linear feet)
Writings, translations, correspondence, printed matter and photographs relating to communism, communism in Yugoslavia, and President Josip Broz Tito.
Djilas, Milovan, 1911-1995.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of some computer media in this collection are available for immediate access. To access sound recordings, video recordings, motion picture material, or other computer media please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980, followed by a large increment in 2014.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Milovan Djilas (1911-1995) was a Yugoslav communist leader who subsequently became the first prominent dissident in the history of communist Eastern Europe.
Djilas said that he “traveled the entire road of communism,” from a youthful revolutionary, partisan guerrilla fighter against Nazi invaders of his native Montenegro, to a zealous believer in Stalinism, to complete disillusionment and rejection of a system “capable of destroying nine-tenths of the human race to ‘make happy’ the one-tenth.” Djilas was for many years the closest associate of Josip Broz Tito, the founder of communist Yugoslavia. It was Djilas who Tito sent to Moscow early in 1948 to inform Stalin that Yugoslavia would follow its own national development, outside the Soviet bloc. Soon, however, the relationship with Tito soured as Djilas became increasingly critical of the party and its ideology. In 1954 he was expelled from the party and his government job and, in the following year, put on trial for “hostile propaganda.” Djilas spent the next four decades in either prison or official isolation.
In 1957 Djilas was able to smuggle his manuscript of The New Class to the West. It was published in English by Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, which was then owned by the author’s friend, William “Bill” Jovanovich. The book made Djilas famous. Eventually translated into sixty languages and having sold three million copies, it was a devastating critique of the communist system. The New Class resulted in another trial and seven-year sentence for “being hostile to the people and the state of Yugoslavia.”
In 1962, Djilas published Conversations with Stalin, which resulted in another prison term. Let out in 1966, he was allowed to travel and spent time in Britain, the United States, and Australia. The Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia in 1968 found him a visiting professor at Princeton. He was highly critical of the Soviets, which on his return to Yugoslavia resulted in the revocation of his passport for the next eighteen years and his living in isolation in Belgrade. The domestic ban on Djilas’s publications was not lifted until 1988, with his full rehabilitation the following year.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains Djilas’s manuscripts and typescripts sent by him to publisher William "Bill" Jovanovich, both published and unpublished, along with correspondence and related materials. There are more than a dozen book manuscripts and numerous essays and articles for the American and Western press. Djilas heavily annotated and corrected most of the manuscripts by hand. Included is the still unpublished English translation of his three-volume novel Worlds and Bridges, and the original Serbian manuscript. Djilas considered this novel about the bloody conflicts between the Serbs and Muslims after World War I his life’s main work. The collection also includes the unpublished Jail Diaries.
The original acquisition contained a typescript of "Nova Klasa: Kritika Savremenog Komunizma," circa 1957, and a photocopy of a typescript of "Druþenje s Titom," 1980, relating to the communist regime in Yugoslavia and to President Josip Broz Tito. They were published under the same titles (Belgrade, 1990; Harrow, England, 1980).
A manuscript and typescript of Djilas's diary from 1953 and 1954 can be found in box 11. The papers also contain rich correspondence, much of which can be found in boxes 17, 18, 27, 28, 42 and 43, as well as scattered throughout the collection.
Index to Writings
Although the papers have not been arranged, this index can serve as a guide to the Djilas writings within the collection.
Djilas wrote a three volume autobiography. The first volume, Land Without Justice, was published in 1958. The second volume was originally titled Rebellious Youth, and was later referred to as Land Without Justice II. In 1973, Memoir of a Revolutionary was published, which combined volumes 2 and 3 of the autobiography. Within the collection, material from the autobiography is listed under all three titles.
13, 28, 38-39 Conversations with Stalin, (Susreti sa Staljinom)
6, 21 Ideas and Times: Political Essays and Articles
37-39 Jail Diaries, (Zatvorski dnevnik)
18-19, 22, 24, 35-36 Land Without Justice, (Beslidna zemlja)
16, 28 The Leper and Other Stories, (Gubavac i druge pripovetke)
13, 30, 40-41 Lost Battles/Under the Colors, (Izgubljene bitke)
3, 4, 22, 34-35 Memoir of a Revolutionary (Pobunjena mladost II; Besudna zemlja, knjiga III)
7, 41-42 Montenegro (Crna Gora)
19-21, 33 Njegoš
1, 11, 22 The New Class
15, 33-34 Paradise Lost, (Izgubljeni raj)
12, 32 Rebellious Youth, (Pobunjena mladost)
10 The Stone and the Violets, (Kamen i ljubičice)
1, 24-25, 36 Tito: The Story From the Inside
2, 29 Thieves’ Fate
19, 28, 31-32 The Unperfect Society: Beyond the New Class, (Nesavršeno društvo)
8, 29 Wartime
5, 23-24, 28, 30, 36-37, 39, 40, 44 Worlds and Bridges (Svetovi I mostovi)
Tito, Josip Broz, 1892-1980.; Communism--Yugoslavia.; Communism.; Dissenters--Yugoslavia.; Yugoslavia--Politics and government--1945-1980.
- Two CD-Rs containing 378 digital image files depicting Milovan Djilas' life and family, circa 1931-1989 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Access
  Original disks closed. Use copies of electronic files available in the Hoover Archives reading room.
- Tito: The Story From the Inside (Druzenje s Titom), annotated typescript, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
- The New Class (Nova klasa), annotated typescript, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
- "Thieves' Fate," annotated typescritpts, undated (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
- "Barovic: Fearlessness Against Lawlessness,", 1979, undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes translation by Mate Mestrovic and edited translation by Drenka Willen
- Articles for New York Times and Esquire, typescripts and clippings, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
  Includes "USSR-China: The Essential Differences," "Yugoslavia:An Economy Still Weighed Down by Dogmatism," and "Testimony of Four Peers"
- Tromedja, 1980 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Memoir of a Revolutionary
  Original English language version, translated and edited by Drenka Willen. Third volume of autobiography.
  - Annotated typescript, 1972 (Box-folder 3: 1-5)
  - Photocopy, 1972 (Box-folder 4: 1-5)
- Worlds and Bridges, (Svetovi I mostovi), Volume III
  - Typescript in Serbo-Croatian, circa 1974 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
  - English translation by Lovett F. Edwards, undated (Box-folder 5: 3-5)
- Ideas and Times: Political Essays and Articles
  - English translation by Dorian Cooke, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
    Includes correspondence and annotated typescripts
  - Annotated typescripts in Serbo-Croatian, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 6: 5-6)
- Montenegro, (Crna Gora)
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, undated (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
  - Annotated typescripts in English, undated (Box-folder 7: 3-5)
- Sound tape reels
  Contains 3 1/4-inch by 7-inch sound tape reels
  - "Reading in English From Recent Prose Work (Introduced by William Jovanovich)," (2 reels), 1968 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Unlabeled reel, undated (Box-folder 8: 2)
- Typescripts, correspondenece, and clippings, 1962-1971 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  Includes "Soviet Power Without Ideology," "The New Left--A Mixture of Enthusiasm and Manipulation," Land Without Justice footnotes, and Montenegro introduction and preface,
- Wartime, correspondence, annotated typescript fragments, and list of corrections, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 8: 4-5)
- "Und wer verandert die Revolutionare," in Christ und Welt, 1969 (Box-folder 8: 6)
- Personal file
  Includes correspondence and clippings
  - 1966 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - 1960-1962 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - 1963 (Box-folder 9: 4)
- The Stone and the Violets, (Kamen i ljubičice)
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, circa 1968 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Annotated typescript, materials not included in published volume, circa 1968 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - Annotated typescript in English, 1972 (Box-folder 10: 3)
    Translated by Lovett F. Edwards
- "Soviet Union Today," typescript, circa 1955-1956 (Box-folder 11: 1)
- Letters to Vlado Dedijer, 1955 (Box-folder 11: 2)
- Notes on Vlado Dedijer, 1955 (Box-folder 11: 3)
- Trial proceedings and Djilas' speech at trial, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 11: 4)
- Letter to Josip Broz Tito, 1967 (Box-folder 11: 5)
- The New Class, first concepts in essays form, annotated typescripts, undated (Box-folder 11: 6)
- "Nordiski San (Nordic Dream)," typescripts and introduction, circa 1954 (Box-folder 11: 7)
- "Sveznanje Gluposti," annotated typescript, undated (Box-folder 11: 8)
- Writings, letter to Vlado Dedijer, and contents list, 1955-1968, undated (Box-folder 11: 9)
- Diary from 1953 to 1954, typescript and manuscript, 1952-1961 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  Includes letter from Stevo Dedijer to Djido
- Rebellious Youth, (Pobunjena mladost), manuscript in Serbo-Croatian, circa 1955 (Box-folder 12: 1-2)
  Second volume of autobiography. See also Box 22.
- Personal file, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 12: 3-5)
  Includes correspondence
- Conversations with Stalin, (Susreti sa Staljinom), annotated typescripts, 1961 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
- Lost Battles, (Izgubljene Bitke), annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, 1967 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
  Published as Under the Colors
- Pre-war writings, typescripts and photocopies, 1931, undated (Box-folder 14: 1-5)
- Pre-war writings, typescripts and photocopies, (cont'd.) (Box-folder 15: 1-2)
- Paradise Lost (Izgubljeni raj)
  Translation by Djilas
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and production notes, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 15: 3)
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, undated (Box-folder 15: 4-5)
- Correspondence
  - Letters to Vlado Dedijer from Djilas, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 16: 1)
  - Letters to senators from William Jovanovich, 1962 (Box-folder 16: 2)
- "The Mountain Wreath," correspondence and introduction, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 16: 3-4)
  Concerns the translation of the Njegoš work into English
- The Leper and Other Stories, (Gubavac i druge pripovetke), typescript, undated (Box-folder 16: 5)
- Correspondence
  See also Box 27
  - 1971 (Box-folder 17: 1)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 17: 2)
  - 1973-1976 (Box-folder 17: 3)
  - 1968 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - 1969 (Box-folder 18: 1)
  - 1970 (Box-folder 18: 2)
- Land Without Justice, Beslidna zemlja
  Volume 3 of autobiography
  - Manuscript in Serbo-Croatian, 1969 (Box-folder 18: 3)
  - Photocopy, undated (Box-folder 18: 4)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Photocopy, undated (Box-folder 19: 1-2)
- The Unperfect Society: Beyond the New Class, (Nesavršeno društvo), annotated typescript and galley, 1969 (Box-folder 19: 3-4)
- Njegoš
  Djilas' study of the 1847 poem of Petar II Petrovic-Njegoš
  - Annotated typescript, undated (Box-folder 19: 5-6)
  - Annotated typescript, fragment, undated (Box-folder 20: 1-2)
- Visit to United States, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 20: 3-4)
- Djilas: The Metamorphosis of a Marxist, typescript by Stephen Clissold, undated (Box-folder 20: 5-6)
- Njegoš, annotated typescript and correspondence, 1961, undated (Box-folder 21: 1-2)
- Ideas and Times: Political Essays and Articles, typescript, 1975 (Box-folder 21: 3)
- Unidentified typescript, undated (Box-folder 21: 4)
  Possibly Leper and Other Stories or Worlds and Bridges
- Pre-war writings, undated (Box-folder 22: 1)
- The New Class, monographs, 1957 (Box-folder 22: 2-3)
- Land Without Justice, Volume 2 (Pobunjena Mladost), manuscript photocopy, circa 1955 (Box-folder 22: 4-5)
  Second volume of autobiography. See also Box 12.
- Worlds and Bridges (Box-folder 23-24)
  - Annotated typescript in English, undated (Box-folder 23: 1-3)
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, undated (Box-folder 23: 4-5)
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, (cont'd.) (Box-folder 24: 1)
- Land Without Justice, annotated typescripts, undated (Box-folder 24: 1-5)
- Tito: The Story From the Inside
  - Annotated galley proofs in English, 1980 (Box-folder 24: 6)
  - Typescript in Serbo-Croatian, 1980 (Box-folder 25: 1-3)
  - Annotated typescript in English, 1980 (Box-folder 25: 4-6)
- Oversize material (Box 26)
  Includes photographs
- Publication of memoir in Serbian, correspondence, 1974 (Box-folder 27: 1)
- Interview, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 27: 2)
- Aleksa Djilas, 1967-1982 (Box-folder 27: 3-4)
- Michael M. Milenkovitch, 1968-1974 (Box-folder 27: 5)
- The Book of Dirges by Matija Bećković, correspondence and typescript, 1976 (Box-folder 27: 6)
  Translated by Momčilo Selić
- Correspondence
  See also Box 17
  - 1966 (Box-folder 27: 7)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 27: 8-9)
  - 1962 (Box-folder 27: 10)
  - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 27: 11)
- The Leper and Other Stories, introduction and correspondence, 1966 (Box-folder 28: 1)
- Correspondence and typescripts
  - 1970-1979 (Box-folder 28: 2)
  - 1968-1970 (Box-folder 28: 3)
  - 1972-1976 (Box-folder 28: 4)
  - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 28: 5)
- Article about Djilas, Encounter Magazine, clipping, undated (Box-folder 28: 6)
- Correspondence
  - The Unperfect Society, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 28: 7)
  - Correspondence with publishers, Milovan Djilas, and Aleksa Djilas, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 28: 8)
  - Worlds and Bridges, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 28: 9)
  - Trip to United States, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 28: 10)
  - Conversations With Stalin, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 28: 11)
  - Rolf Hochhuth, 1967 (Box-folder 28: 12)
  - 1977-1979 (Box-folder 29: 1)
- "Civil War Years," printed copy, 1977 (Box-folder 29: 2)
- "Thieves' Fate," typescripts and correspondence, 1978 (Box-folder 29: 3)
- Wartime, (Revolucionarni Rat), annotated typescript, 1975 (Box-folder 29: 4-5)
- Worlds and Bridges, annotated typescript, 1971 (Box-folder 30: 1-3)
- Under the Colors, index cards, undated (Box-folder 30: 4)
  Other titles include "Lost Battles"
- Monographs, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 30: 5)
- Monographs (cont'd.) (Box-folder 31: 1-3)
- The Unperfect Society
  - Annotated typescripts and notes, undated (Box-folder 31: 4-5)
  - Photocopy, 1968 (Box-folder 32: 1)
- Unidentified typescript, undated (Box-folder 32: 2)
- Rebellious Youth, typescript in English, undated (Box-folder 32: 3-5)
- Njegoš, annotated typescript, undated (Box-folder 33: 1-2)
- Paradise Lost
  - Photocopy and notes (Box-folder 33: 5)
  - Photocopy and notes (cont'd.) (Box-folder 34: 1)
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, undated (Box-folder 34: 2-3)
- Correspondence and subject files
  - Stefanija Djilas, 1965 (Box-folder 34: 4)
  - Aleksa Djilas, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 34: 5)
  - Introduction to The Leper and Other Stories and review of book by Victor Gollanz, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 34: 6)
  - Drenka Willen, Belgrade trip, 1967-1978 (Box-folder 34: 7)
  - Marver H. Bernstein, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 34: 8)
  - Desimir Tochitch, 1980 (Box-folder 34: 9)
  - Ethnic composition of Yugoslavia, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 34: 10)
  - Vane Ivanovic, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 34: 11)
  - Trip to Belgrade, William Jovanovich, notebook, 1967 (Box-folder 34: 12)
  - Roksanda Cerovic's visa, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 34: 13)
  - Croatian book, Vane Ivanovic, 1975 (Box-folder 34: 14)
  - General correspondence, 1970-1975 (Box-folder 34: 15)
- Memoir of a Revolutionary
  - Page proofs in English, 1973 (Box-folder 34: 16)
  - Page proofs in English (cont'd.) (Box-folder 35: 1)
  - Galley proofs in English, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 35: 2)
- Subject file
  - Jovan Barovic, 1966-1982 (Box-folder 35: 3)
  - Matija Beckovic, 1976 (Box-folder 35: 4)
  - Biography of Djilas by Daniel Ivin, 1972-1976 (Box-folder 35: 5)
- Land Without Justice
  - Correspondence, 1956-1962 (Box-folder 35: 6)
  - Correspondence (cont'd.) (Box-folder 36: 1)
  - Reviews and introduction, 1958 (Box-folder 36: 3)
- Interviews of Djilas
  - John Morgan, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 36: 4)
  - Radio Liberty, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 36: 5-6)
  - Life interview, printed copy, 1970 (Box-folder 36: 7)
- Trip to Yugoslavia, 1975 (Box-folder 36: 8)
  Includes bibliography
- Willam Jovanovich's appearance before a senate hearing, 1962 (Box-folder 36: 8)
- Bibliography and contract information, 1975 (Box-folder 36: 9)
- Imprisonment of Djilas, clippings, 1958-1962 (Box-folder 36: 10)
- Tito: The Story From the Inside, clippings, 1980 (Box-folder 36: 11)
- Djilas correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 36: 12)
- Worlds and Bridges, Volume 2, annotated typescript in English, 1974 (Box-folder 36: 13)
- Worlds and Bridges, Volume 2, annotated typescript in English (cont'd.) (Box-folder 37: 1-2)
- Jail Diaries (Zatvorski dnevnik)
  - Typescript in Serbo-Croatian, part 1 (1958-1961), undated (Box-folder 37: 3-4)
    Unpublished
  - Typescript in Serbo-Croatian, part 2 (Zatvorske Beleske, 1962-1966), undated (Box-folder 37: 5)
  - Typescript in Serbo-Croatian, part 2 (Zatvorske Beleske, 1962-1966) (cont'd.) (Box-folder 38: 1)
- Conversations with Stalin
  - Annotated typescripts, notes, correspondence, and memoranda, 1961-1968, undated (Box-folder 38: 2-3)
  - Galley proofs, 1961 (Box-folder 38: 4)
  - Annotated galley proofs, author's set, 1961 (Box-folder 38: 5)
    Possibly the galleys which William Jovanovich delivered to Belgrade to be corrected by Djilas
  - Correspondence and clippings, 1962 (Box-folder 39: 1)
- Jail Diaries, photocopy and memo, undated (Box-folder 39: 2-3)
- Worlds and Bridges, typescript in Serbo-Croatian, undated (Box-folder 39: 4-5)
- Worlds and Bridges, typescript in Serbo-Croatian (cont'd.) (Box-folder 40: 1-3)
- Lost Battles, annotated typescript and list of corrections, 1967 (Box-folder 40: 4)
- Lost Battles, annotated typescript and list of corrections (cont'd.) (Box-folder 41: 1-2)
- Montenegro
  - Annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, undated (Box-folder 41: 3-4)
  - Annotated galley proofs in English, undated (Box-folder 41: 5)
  - Galley proofs in English, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 42: 1)
  - Galley proofs of novel excerpt, "The Eve of the Battle,", 1962 (Box-folder 42: 2)
    Published in limited edition as a New Year's greeting
- Correspondence
  - 1968 (Box-folder 42: 3-7)
    Includes letters related to visits and speaking engagements
  - 1968, 1973 (Box-folder 43: 1-4)
- Miscellaneous, 1971-1979 (Box-folder 43: 5)
  Includes typescript of Časovnik
- Worlds and Bridges, annotated typescript in Serbo-Croatian, 1973 (Box-folder 44: 1-2)
  "Brought from Belgrade by Peter Jovanovich"